<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>England's call to thankfulness for her great deliverance from popery and arbitrary power by the glorious conduct of the Prince of Orange (now King of England) in the year 1688 in a sermon preach'd in the parish-church of Almer in Dorsetshire on February the 14th, 1688/9 / by John Olliffe ...</title>
            <author>Ollyffe, John, 1647-1717.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1689</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 68 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 19 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53335</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O288</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17619</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13162279</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13162279</idno>
            <idno type="VID">98198</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53335)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 98198)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 431:9)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>England's call to thankfulness for her great deliverance from popery and arbitrary power by the glorious conduct of the Prince of Orange (now King of England) in the year 1688 in a sermon preach'd in the parish-church of Almer in Dorsetshire on February the 14th, 1688/9 / by John Olliffe ...</title>
                  <author>Ollyffe, John, 1647-1717.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for Jonathan Robinson ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1689.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Advertisement on p. [1] at end.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
               <term>Great Britain --  History --  William and Mary, 1689-1702 --  Sermons.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-10</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="half_title">
            <pb facs="tcp:98198:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:98198:1"/>
            <p>A Thankſgiving-Sermon, FOR Deliverance of this Kingdom FROM <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Power.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:98198:2"/>
            <head>The Publiſher to the Reader.</head>
            <p>THIS <hi>Sermon</hi> had been publiſhed ſooner had not the Carrier <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>ept it ſeveral Weeks in his Hands before he delivered it; yet I hope the pious Reader will not think it comes too late for publick <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ſe, when he conſiders the Oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion and the Matter of it, and how excellently well it is managed by the Reverend Author.</p>
            <p>So great and amazing are the Providences of God towards us in <hi>England</hi> in delivering us from <hi>Popery</hi> and <hi>Arbitrary Power,</hi> by the glorious Conduct of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> (now our <hi>Gratious King</hi>) that diſcourſes of this Nature (which ſo well repreſent the Glories of this Deliverance) ſhould never be eſteemed unſeaſonable, and 'tis hop'd the <hi>Wiſdom of the Nation</hi> will make the Duty of Thankful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs anniverſary on this account, that ſo the preſent and future Generations may <hi>praiſe the Lord for his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and for his wonderful Works to us the Children of Men in this Iſland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I heartily wiſh our preſent <hi>Murmurers</hi> (commonly called <hi>Grumbletonians</hi>) would but ſeriouſly conſider how conſpicuouſly the <hi>Wiſdom, Power and Goodneſs</hi> of God appear in the late Revolutions, I think then they would be convinced (if they do not wilfully ſhut their Eyes againſt the Beams of Divine Majeſty) how great their Sin is in <hi>provoking the great God at the Red-Sea, even at the Red-Sea of our Deliverance,</hi> by hankering after the Onions and Garlick of <hi>Egypt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I pray God open all our Eyes that we may know in this our Day, the things that belong to our Peace, before they be hid from us. <hi>Amen.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:98198:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>ENGLAND's CALL TO THANKFULNESS, FOR Her Great DELIVERANCE FROM POPERY and ARBITRARY POWER, By the Glorious Conduct of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> (now King of <hi>England</hi>) in the Year 1688.</p>
            <p>In a Sermon preach'd in the Pariſh-Church of <hi>Almer</hi> in <hi>Dorſetſhire,</hi> on <hi>February</hi> the 14th, 1688/9</p>
            <p>By <hi>JOHN OLLIFFE,</hi> RECTOR there.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON;</hi> printed for <hi>Ionathan Robinſon,</hi> at the Golden Lion in St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s Church-Yard, <abbr>MDCLXXXIX.</abbr>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:98198:3"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:98198:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>PSALM cxxvi. <hi>ver.</hi> 3.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <q>The Lord hath done great things for us, whereof we are glad.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>THE Deſign of our aſſembling toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther at this time, is to render Thanks to Almighty God, for the late great Deliverance which he has wrought for us, from the ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tile and dangerous Attempts of our Popiſh Enemies to ſubvert our Government and Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion, and to implore his farther Bleſſing and Aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, that that may be perfected, which is ſo hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pily begun. And ſurely if we have been awake to take notice of things, if we have had our Eyes open to ſee and obſerve the ſeveral Tranſactions of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, which have been in our Behalf in this reſpect, we cannot but think this a very reaſonable Service. And you will eaſily perceive the Words which I have read to you out of the Pſalmiſt to be a fit Subject of my Diſcourſe upon this occaſion.</p>
            <p>This Pſalm was compoſed, as appeareth by the ſubject matter of it, at the return of the Jewiſh Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple from <hi>Babylon,</hi> after their long and hard Bondage there; which was a Mercy of ſo great and ſtrange a Nature, that it filled them with Admiration and Aſtoniſhment to conſider of it, that they could ſcarce
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:98198:4"/>believe their own Eyes and Ears in what they heard and ſaw, but were ſo ſurprized with it, that they thought it to be but a Dream or Deluſion of their own Fancies: <hi>ver.</hi> 1. <hi>When the Lord turned again the Captivity</hi> Sion, <hi>we were like them that dream.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And the Heathen were as much amazed and ſtartled at it as they, <hi>ver.</hi> 2. <hi>For then ſaid they among the Heathens, The Lord hath done great things for them.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>It was the wonder of all, that an Heathen Empe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rour of his own free motion ſhould ſet at Liberty a captive People, and ſend them to their own Land, a People deſpiſed and ſcorned of all; when it had been eſteemed the Policy of all the former Kings to deſtroy and ruin that ſingular ſort of Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, that was ſeparate from all People, that had been the great Eye-ſore of all the Nations about. And this mighty Prince doth not only freely diſcharge them, and ſend them back into their own Country, but aſſiſts them in the building of their Temple, and ſetting up the Worſhip of the true God of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> whoſe Ordinances were different from all People: well might they therefore be amazed and wonder at ſo ſtrange a Revolution and turn of things.</p>
            <p>And here in this verſe now they aſcribe and attri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute all to God, they own it to be his Work, though <hi>Cyrus</hi> was the Inſtrument; and that it was a great Work indeed, which rightly called for Joy and Thankfulneſs. <hi>The Lord hath done great things for us, whereof we are glad.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And that which the Jews here ſay in their Thankſgiving and Praiſe, I think we of this Nation have cauſe likewiſe to ſay at this time, <hi>viz. That the Lord hath done great things for us;</hi> and that there is juſtly due to him a Tribute of delightful Praiſe now, as there was from them then.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="3" facs="tcp:98198:4"/>Let us conſider therefore,</p>
            <p n="1">I. The great Things that God hath done for us. And,</p>
            <p n="2">II. The Praiſe that is due to him for the ſame.</p>
            <p n="1">I. Let us conſider the great Things that God hath done for us: which will appear to be great indeed, if we conſider them even nakedly in themſelves, and much more if they are conſidered in their Circum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Firſt,</hi> The Things which God hath done for us, are very great in themſelves. For it is no leſs, than the ſaving of our Engliſh Government from appa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Ruin, the recovering of our Rights from Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitrary Invaſions; the ſecuring of our Liberties and Properties, and above all the preſerving our Religion, which was in manifeſt Hazard of being undermined and deſtroyed, and the preventing the Maſſacres and Bloodſhed, which probably muſt have attended the ſame.</p>
            <p>It is agreed on all hands, that the Engliſh Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment was in the way to ruin; the force of Laws, even in themſelves as Laws, was enervated, and ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny mortal Blows were given to the Legiſlative Power it ſelf in its very Fundamentals; and the Rights of Men imbodied in Corporations, and the particular Liberties of Perſons were no longer ſecure to any, when once they ſtood in Competition with Popiſh Deſigns.</p>
            <p>But this inſlaving of our Bodies, and depriving us of our outward Rights was the leaſt of thoſe Miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries that were growing upon us, and which we were
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:98198:5"/>already in part groaning under: That which is worſe, is the Inſlaving of our Souls and Conſciences, by a mighty Power, which goeth to check-mate it with Almighty God himſelf. This was coming on us amain, like an overflowing Deluge invading the Land. For thoſe that think moſt moderately of the Adminiſtration of things before, muſt allow, that all that Liberty that was promiſed or given, was no farther intended, than as it was hoped it might be an Introduction to a more Arbitrary Invaſion of our Laws, and a means of Eſtabliſhment and Increaſe of the Romiſh Religion among us.</p>
            <p>And it is well known, what the Nature of that Religion is, when once it hath got the Power in its Hands, it will ſuffer none to ſtand by it, whatever Laws, Proviſions, or Promiſes are made for the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curing of any other; as is apparent from the Popiſh Management in the Neighbour-Nation, where ſuch a Perſecution hath been ſet afoot, and carried on againſt the Proteſtant Party, as the Tongue of Man is not able to expreſs, nor the Pen of any to depaint in its right Colours. And neither the Merits of that Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, nor the Edicts and Laws, that were in their Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vour, could ward it off; which is an Evidence, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides the many ſanguinary Proceedings and bloody Maſſacres that have been before executed in that and other Popiſh Countries, what we muſt have look'd for when once that Religion had got the Aſcendant over us, that it had been out of Fear of Danger it ſelf: What could we then have expected, but that Priſons and Racks, Confiſcation of Goods, and Fire and Sword muſt have been our Portion, as well as our Neighbours, having alſo had ſo many Teſtimonies and Marks of their Kindneſs to us in former Ages at home.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="5" facs="tcp:98198:5"/>But we have cauſe to fear, that this would not on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly have been the end of this Religion, when once it could have come to its Growth and Eſtabliſhment, which muſt have been a long time firſt, if that was to be procured by ordinary and common Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thods.</p>
            <p>But the fiery Zeal of our Enemies was too rapid and fierce to be contained within the ordinary Bounds of ſlow and uſual Methods; we muſt have expected it to have broken out far beyond; and it is not to be doubted, but if they could have been ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure of their Arms at home, and of a Fleet at Sea to have ſerved the Deſign, or as ſoon as they could have ordered the matter, that it would have been ſo, there ſhould a forreign Force have then joyned with them; and we ſhould have had Swords and Guns to have converted Proteſtants, which Arguments and Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons had been too dull Tools to effect: what the Poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticks could not have brought about, ſhould have been attempted by main Might.</p>
            <p>And what between the Prerogative of a bigotted Prince, the Sentence of corrupt Judges, the Colour and Favour of Laws to be procured for Popiſh Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice, and the Violence of an armed Force, poor Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants could have expected nothing elſe, but to have been ground to peices, as between ſo many Mil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtones: And this was coming upon us a-pace, if our Almighty Deliverer had not procured for us a Reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy in good time.</p>
            <p>And if once <hi>England</hi> had become a Prey to Popiſh Rage, which hath been juſtly eſteemed the great Bulwark of the Reformation, the Proteſtant States abroad had not been like to ſubſiſt long, but in hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mane proſpect of things muſt have undergone the ſame Fate.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:98198:6"/>And whoſe Heart would not ake then to conſider the Power and Prevalence that the Romiſh Religion ſhould have had, not only among us, but all Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtendom over, if God had not put a ſtop to its riſing Greatneſs, and beat off the Chariot Wheels, by which our Enemies did drive ſo faſt; and in the nick of time drown the <hi>Egyptians</hi> before they could overtake his <hi>Iſrael?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The glorious Reformation, which hath ſo long ſhined with a mighty Luſtre, muſt then have ſet in obſcure Darkneſs. And thoſe Proteſtants that would ſtill have kept the Faith and a good Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, muſt have run to Caves and Holes of the Earth for Shelter, for there had been no longer any place of abode for them in the City that is ſet on a Hill.</p>
            <p>Then you muſt have been bowing your Knees to Idols again, and falling down before Stocks and Stones, or would have had ſuch a weight of Oppreſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Cruelties laid on, that would have broke your very Backs; and if we could not admit to bear the Load of all the Popiſh Superſtitions, we ſhould have had a Load of another Nature, that without the Strength of Martyrs we muſt needs have fallen under. We muſt have taken the Mark of the Beaſt in our Foreheads, or we ſhould hardly have bought and ſold in the Markets.</p>
            <p>Then Traditions and Canons muſt have been our Rule, rather than the Holy Scriptures: Yea, we ſhould not have been allowed to have believed our own Senſes, nor to have made uſe of the moſt natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Right which belongs to us as rational Creatures, to have judged for our ſelves, but muſt have ſubmitted Senſe, Reaſon, Conſcience, Scripture, and all to a pretended infallible Judge, though we know not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:98198:6"/>how he came by his Infallibility, nor can ſee any thing in the World that he hath to ſay for it, but big Words, and proud Boaſts: But we muſt have put out our own Eyes, and yet have been forc'd to have fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed blind Guides. If we had kept the Founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, we muſt have had Hay and Stubble built upon it; and then if ever we had been ſaved, it muſt needs have been with the greateſt Difficulty imaginable.</p>
            <p>We and our Children muſt have been nurtur'd up with corrupt Doctrines, and falſe and lying Legends, inſtead of being fed with the ſincere Milk of the Word. You muſt have had half Sacraments, and Latin Prayers, that you ſhould not have underſtood what you had been about; and you muſt have wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped a little piece of Dough for a God, conjured into a Deity by five words of the Prieſt, when you may have as good an one your ſelves in your own Cupboards.</p>
            <p>And if you could not have turned Papiſts throughly, then at leaſt you muſt have turned Hypocrites, and diſſembled before God and the World, or elſe a Cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſado of red Coats and Dragoons fit for the purpoſe would have tried their skill upon you.</p>
            <p>But all this and much more, which might be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſented, our gracious Saviour hath mercifully pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vented; and not only ſo, but we have good hopes of ſuch an Eſtabliſhment and Settlement, that all our other Grievances may be redreſſed likewiſe; and Peace and Righteouſneſs may flouriſh in our Land.</p>
            <p>I have good hopes, that we ſhall not only be fe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oured from the Fears of Popery and Slavery, but that we may ſee a long-look'd-for bleſſed Union among Proteſtants, and Religion, in its Power and Purity in good Reputation among us, that it ſhall be a thing
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:98198:7"/>of as bad a Name to be a wicked Man, as to be a Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt. It hath been a mighty Work which hath been done already; and that will give us Encouragement to hope for more, if we thankfully accept and im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prove that which is begun.</p>
            <p>You will all allow, that theſe are great things in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, there being nothing that is more dear to Men, then the ſaving of Life, Liberty and Religion. But theſe great things hath God done for us in this his wonderful Diſpenſation at this time.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Secondly,</hi> It will appear that God hath done great things for us, if we conſider the Circumſtances.</p>
            <p>As that it was at a time, when our Enemies were bold and confident, when they thought all things ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cure to themſelves, and paſt danger of miſcarrying; they had the Advice and Aſſiſtance of that Society, and Order of Men, that have been cryed up in this laſte Age, for being expert in all the Arts of Policy. They have been framing and laying, and turning and winding this Plot of extirpating the Northern He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reſy for a long time.</p>
            <p>The Softneſs and Fearfulneſs of the firſt of the two Royal Brothers was indeed ſome Hindrance to them: but now they had got a Prince, whoſe eager and fiery Spirit, animated with Popiſh Zeal, reſolved to accompliſh the Deſign, or himſelf to die a Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyr for the impious Cauſe.</p>
            <p>Some of them in the former Reign have been heard to ſay, that the Plot was laid ſo deep, that all the Devils in Hell were not able to hinder it. And indeed ſo far they were partly in the right; for then Satan ſhould have been divided againſt himſelf, it being the Intereſt and Buſineſs only of that black Kingdom; but they have found there is a God
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:98198:7"/>in Heaven, that hath been able to fruſtrate all their Deſigns.</p>
            <p>But they however were confident and big with Expectation of Succeſs; and ſome have given out very bold Words, that we muſt either burn or turn, and that it were the better way to come over to them in time by Perſwaſion, than ſtay till we were com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pelled by Force.</p>
            <p>For the Deſign that was laid, was the Fruit of their long and beſt Counſels; ſo that now at laſt they lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle doubled but all would be theirs, and they began already in Imagination to divide the Spoil among themſelves. Now to have all theſe Hopes diſappoint<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and to have all theſe Counſels diſannulled, is cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly a very great thing.</p>
            <p>Then conſider on the other ſide, that we were al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt hopeleſs of finding any Remedy. A Faintneſs and Diſpiritedneſs had ſeized the Nation; they ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving been ſo long time uſed to Infringements of their Rights, to Burdens and Oppreſſions, that the bear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of them now was almoſt grown natural by being common, and ſo became to be the more eaſily en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dured. Many indeed of Superiour Quality, and of tender Reſentments, could not but look on with Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>content, but knew not how to help.</p>
            <p>On their parts 'tis true there had not been many Converts, but what they could not get in Perſons of their own Religion, they found in ſuch as had none at all, who being therefore put in places of Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicature and Truſt, would ſerve their Deſigns as well or better than their own moſt Religious Votaries.</p>
            <p>So that the Law was perverted to favour their ſide. There were Armies, and Troops to prevent Inſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: A great number of the beſt Proteſtants were
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:98198:8"/>lulled aſleep by the preſent Eaſe that they had, like Perſons wearied after long Labour, and now were glad to ſit down and be at reſt. Others had been hamſtrung with pretty uncouth Doctrines, that though they were in pain, yet had no mind to move either hand or Foot.</p>
            <p>And then above all, there was a mighty <hi>Nimrod</hi> beyond the Seas, to eſpouſe and carry on the Project, and is one who had been long fluſh'd, both with Cruelty and Succeſs.</p>
            <p>So that what could we hope, unleſs Help ſhould come from the Clouds? And we had no thought of Miracles. But ſuch indeed, and no leſs hath ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peared in theſe great Things, that God hath done for us.</p>
            <p>Conſider again, Here is a Deliverance, ſudden, unexpected, hardly thought of; ſo that it may be well applied, what is here ſaid by the <hi>Jews</hi> at their Deliverance out of Captivity, we are like them that dream, when our Adverſaries Confidence and our own Fears would not give us leave to hope. God hath been ſeen in the Mount, juſt when we were appointed for Sacrifice: and our Soul is eſcaped as a Bird out of the Snare of the Fowler, the Snare is broken and we are eſcaped.</p>
            <p>Conſider moreover the manner, in what a ſtrange and unheard-of way it hath been, as well as ſudden and unhoped for. All this glorious Scene of Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels and Arts is taken down as it were in a Moment, and almoſt diſappears. That which we have ſeen contriving and promoting for ſo long time, how ſoon is it unravelled! and the Work of ſo many Years is undone almoſt before you can think how.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="11" facs="tcp:98198:8"/>And yet hardly any Blood ſpilt in the caſe, or but very little; when we could not have thought, but that a Sea of Blood muſt have flowed in upon us, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the Banks of Right and Juſtice could have been ſet up again, which were fallen down.</p>
            <p>But though our Adverſaries ſtorm and fret never ſo much, our Deliverance is wrought; and thoſe whom we had cauſe to fear moſt from, as the Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments of our Miſchief, come to be our Helpers, whereby the long Train of Popiſh Contrivances is blown away like Chaff: and the Pit which they had digged for others, they are fallen into themſelves: and the proud Scorners have been filled with their own ways.</p>
            <p>Yea, our Deliverance hath been carried on farther than we could expect, even after it was begun, and we have hopes of more yet; and thoſe things which have ſeemed to be Hindrances and Lets in the way, may prove the greateſt Furtherances to the moſt hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>py End.</p>
            <p>It is to be hoped, that all will grow wiſer after all that long dear-bought Experience, which we have had of the evil of our Diviſions; and that neither Party will think ſo hardly of one another for the time to come, as they have done. But that ways will be found out to compoſe our Religious Jars and Differences, that we may like Brethren live together in Unity. And then ſhall we become as a City com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pact within it ſelf; which is never in ſo great Dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger, as from inteſtine Fouds and Quarrels.</p>
            <p>But now that the Mercy which we have received may be more inherent in our Apprehenſions, com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare the Condition of our poor Brethren in other parts, and what they have ſuffered, whilſt we are de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>livered.
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:98198:9"/>We have had a Cloud over us, that hath been no bigger in Compariſon than a Man's hand (though others have been gathering about) and have had but a few Drops in compariſon falling upon us: whilſt it hath been with them a Day of Blackneſs and Darkneſs, of Gloomineſs and thick Darkneſs; the whole Heavens have been filled with Clouds and Rain, with Storms and Tempeſts, ſo that they have not ſeen the Sun nor Stars for many Days; a very bitter Cup hath been wrung out to them, which we have hardly ſipt of, but they have drunk the very Dregs; and who can tell, what may be the Portion of our Brethren in the Neighbour Kingdom under the ſame Government with our ſelves, who muſt needs be ſighing ſtill in fearful and dreadful Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, whilſt to us it is <hi>a good Day?</hi> We have an ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Help and Salvation wrought, which they can ſee yet but at a Diſtance: And 'tis well if their Hopes can over-ballance their Fears.</p>
            <p>And muſt we not ſay then, that all this is a migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Work, and that God hath done great things for us? Long and laſting Miſeries and Calamities did ſorely threaten us, neither could we ſee any preſent Help at hand. But God put forth his Voice, and called back the proud Waters, that they have not prevailed over us. He hath brought us out, and hath ſet our Feet in a large place: Our Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is vindicated from Tyranny and Uſurpation; our Liberties and Rights reſcued out of the Hands of Invaders; our Religion preſerved, which we were afraid would have been loſt: and we hope all will be but the more furbiſh'd up, and rendred brighter by thoſe Rubs and Oppoſitions that it hath met with.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="13" facs="tcp:98198:9"/>And muſt not we ſay, that theſe are great things? when the deepeſt Policies have been defeated; Arms and Power have been turned againſt the Uſers; a Deliverance wrought, and yet ſo little Effuſion of Blood in the procuring of it. The Minds, Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels, and Policies of Men turned about upon a ſud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den: A mighty Revolution, and yet almoſt with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any noiſe: A new Face of things appears, which looks beautiful, though it be not yet fully filled up.</p>
            <p n="2">II. Now let us conſider then the Praiſe that is due to God for all this, for all theſe great Things that he hath done for us. For this Gladneſs, which is in our Hearts, ſhould flow out in Praiſes to God; for that is the beſt Expreſſion both of Gladneſs and Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude; which in ſuch a caſe ſhould always go toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Oh clap your hands, all ye People, ſhout unto God with the Voice of Triumph. For the Lord moſt high is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rible, he is a great King over all the Earth: Sing Praiſes to God, ſing Praiſes; Sing Praiſes unto our King, ſing Praiſes: God reigneth over the Heathen, God ſitteth upon the Throne of his Holineſs: He is our Refuge and Strength, a very preſent Help in Trouble. The Lord of Hoſts is with us, the God of</hi> Jacob <hi>is our Refuge. Selah.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now there are theſe four things to be conſider<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed in that Praiſe, which is due from us to God at this time.</p>
            <p n="1">1. It is to be acknowledged and confeſſed by us, that it is his Work, that it is he that hath done theſe great Things for us, though it hath been by the Inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vention of Means, which he works, as he commonly doth; yet theſe Means are of his providing, chooſing,
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:98198:10"/>exciting; and become proſperous by his Aſſiſting and Bleſſing; and therefore though Means are to be valued and honoured in their places, yet it is to God that the principal Tribute of Praiſe belongs.</p>
            <p>And in all ſuch caſes, we find that this hath been the Method of the Church, to give God the Honour.</p>
            <p>When <hi>Moſes</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> brought the Children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> out of <hi>Egypt, Moſes</hi> was an eminent Inſtru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, he was their Counſellour and Captain, yet the Glory of the Deliverance is aſcribed to God, and theſe were but the Means: <hi>Thou leddeſt thy People, like a Flock,</hi> ſay they, <hi>by the Hand of</hi> Moſes <hi>and</hi> Aa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ron, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 77.20.</p>
            <p>So in the Victories of <hi>Deborah</hi> and <hi>Barak</hi> over <hi>Jabin</hi> and <hi>Siſera, Praiſe ye the Lord,</hi> ſay they, <hi>for the avenging of Iſrael,</hi> Judg 5.2.</p>
            <p>And ſo always, when ever any Deliverer was raiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed up, or any Deliverance wrought, it is obſerved as the Lords doing ſtill: <hi>For this God is our God for ever and ever,</hi> Pſal. 48.14.</p>
            <p>And therefore, <hi>Happy art thou, O</hi> Iſrael, <hi>who is like unto thee, O People ſaved of the Lord, the Shield of thy Help, and the Sword of thy Excellency! And therefore thine Enemies ſhall be found Liers unto thee, and thou ſhalt tread upon their high places;</hi> as <hi>Moſes</hi> ſpeaks in his Bleſſing of the People, <hi>Deut.</hi> 33. <hi>ult.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And this is the Churches conſtant Opinion and Senſe of things, as appears in that <hi>Pſal.</hi> 124. which is calculated for any times of Deliverance; <hi>If it had not been the Lord, who was on our ſide, now may</hi> Iſrael <hi>ſay; If it had not been the Lord, who was on our ſide, when Men roſe up againſt us, then they had ſwallowed us up quick, when their Wrath was kindled againſt us: our Help is in the Name of the Lord, who made Heaven and
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:98198:10"/>Earth.</hi> The like may we now ſay; and it is unto God therefore that we muſt give the Glory of all that Mercy, that we have received as the principal Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thor, Exciter, Promoter, &amp; Worker of our Deliverance.</p>
            <p>And there are ſeveral Things, that do manifeſtly ſpeak the Divine Counſel, and Power, and Providence to have been eminently in all this Affair, in that there hath been ſuch a ſtrange Concurrence of all things to bring it about to the paſs that 'tis now in.</p>
            <p>As beſides the more remote Providences of former Years, the preſent Ability and Wealth of that Neigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour State, by whoſe Counſel and Aſſiſtance our great Deliverer under God was enabled to undertake this Enterprize, they being together embark'd in the ſame common Proteſtant Intereſt with our ſelves.</p>
            <p>And then the Concurrence of the States about in the ſame Deſign, all the Proteſtants expecting to un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dergo the ſame Fate with us.</p>
            <p>And moreover a general Union of the Popiſh Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernours themſelves againſt the <hi>French Nimrod,</hi> upon whoſe Aſſiſtance the Popiſh Farty at home did build their Hopes, as from him they had derived their Counſels; and the very Winds and Elements made to conſpire for the convenient Paſſage of the Troops that were engaged to help us.</p>
            <p>And ſuch an Union of all Parties, that duly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered of things among our ſelves, either to join in with the forreign Helps, or at leaſt not to oppoſe them, as hath not been known in this Nation for a great while paſt.</p>
            <p>For there was an Univerſal, either Suſpicion or Diſcontent in all Parties againſt the Power, that is now fallen, for fear either of its Frauds or Violences.</p>
            <p>And it pleaſed God to enlighten at perſwade thoſe
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:98198:11"/>that were able to do moſt hurt by the Arms that they were impowered with, not to concur with Uſurpa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Tyranny to the Ruin of their Country, but rather to give an helping hand by an amicable Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>junction with thoſe that ſought its Preſervation.</p>
            <p>And ſuch a wiſe Counſel and Conduct hath been purſued in the Affair all along; and ſuch Shame and Guilt, ſuch Diſtruſt and Trembling ſeized upon our Adverſaries, that there hath been nothing conſidera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly to ſtop the coming of this Matter to ſuch a bleſſed Iſſue as we could not foreſee. So that that is come to paſs, which neither they did fear at firſt, nor we could hope.</p>
            <p>That proud and fierce Jeſuit, that ſtood ſo near the Throne, hath been heard to make a mock of Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence, when in Diſcourſe one ſaid to him, that God in his Providence would take care to maintain that Party, that had Juſtice on its ſide: He replied ſcoffingly, <hi>What do you talk of Providence now a-days?</hi> But he hath found there hath been a great and wiſe Providence that hath over-ruled all, and hath outdone all his Counſels and Policies.</p>
            <p>And it is our parts then, to aſcribe the Glory of all to this Holy and wiſe Providence, as being in ſuch an eminent manner concerned in bringing all about, which we now hear and ſee; in putting ſuch a Spirit of Counſel and Courage in our great Deliverer, pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viding ſufficient Means and Aſſiſtance, and uniting all both at home and abroad to comply with the Un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertaking, or not to make any conſiderable Oppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: Surely <hi>this is the Lord's Doing, and it ought to be marvellous in our Eyes. Oh ſing unto the Lord a new Song; ſing unto the Lord all the Earth, Sing unto the Lord, bleſs his Name, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>and ſhew forth his Salvation
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:98198:11"/>from day to day; For the Lord is great, and greatly to be praiſed; He is to be feared above all Gods, Honour and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jeſty are before him; Strength and Beauty are in his San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuary: Give unto the Lord, O ye Kindreds of the Peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, give unto the Lord Glory and Strength; Give unto the Lord the Glory due unto his Name; bring an Offering, and come into his Courts: Say among the Heathen, that the Lord reigneth; the World alſo ſhall be eſtabliſhed, that it ſhall not be moved, he ſhall judg the People righteouſly.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The next thing then to be conſidered in this Duty of Praiſe is, that as we acknowledg it to be God's Act, ſo that we acknowledg it alſo to be an Act of free Grace, and mere undeſerved Mercy to us; ſo that we muſt every way ſay, <hi>Not unto us, O Lord, not unto us, but unto thy Name be given the Glory.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>As our Help cometh of God, for vain elſe would be the Help of Man; ſo we muſt acknowledg, that it is of God's mere Mercy that we are thus delivered, and that we are not conſumed: It is only becauſe his Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſions fail not.</p>
            <p>This muſt always be remembred, as <hi>Moſes</hi> alſo tells the <hi>Jews</hi> upon their getting the Land of <hi>Canaan,</hi> Deut. 9.4. <hi>Speak not thou in thy Heart, after that the Lord thy God hath caſt out theſe Nations from before thee, ſaying, For my Righteouſneſs the Lord hath brought me in to poſſeſs this Land: But for the Wickedneſs of theſe Nations the Lord doth drive them out from before thee; Not for thy Righteouſneſs, or for the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>prightneſs of thine Heart doſt thou go to poſſeſs the Land; but for the Wickedneſs of theſe Nations the Lord doth drive them out from before thee,</hi> &amp;c. Whether it be for their Sins or no, that there hath been ſuch a ſtrange change and Revolution among us, I will not determine; but I am ſure it is not for our Merits.</p>
            <p>For I doubt we have cauſe enough to lament and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſs with Shame and Confuſion, as <hi>Ezra</hi> did the Sins of
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:98198:12"/>the People of the <hi>Jews,</hi> Ezr. 9.6. <hi>O my God, I am aſhamed and bluſh to lift up my Face to thee my God: For our Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quities are increaſed over our Heads, and our Treſpaſs is grown up unto the Heavens: Since the Days of our Fathers have we been in a great Treſpaſs unto this Day.</hi> And therefore we muſt ſay as he, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. that it is all of Mercy, that we have been delivered from any Evil, that <hi>Grace hath been ſhewn us from the Lord our God, to leave us a Remnant to eſcape, and to give us a Nail in his Holy Place, that our God may lighten our Eyes, and give us a little reviving in our Bondage.</hi> And <hi>God hath not forſaken us, but hath ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended Mercy unto us.</hi> It is all Grace and Mercy, and not Worthineſs and Merit on our parts.</p>
            <p>There have been, bleſſed be God, many pious pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Perſons amongſt us, that have been earneſt with God for Mercy and Settlement to the Land. But how many more are there that have been Curſers, Swearers, A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>theiſts and prophane Wretches, that have not had the Fear of God before their Eyes: And we may well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mire, that the Oaths and Blaſphemies of the many have not outcryed the Prayers of the few.</p>
            <p>Swearing is a mere Defiance of Heaven without any conſiderable Temptation, having nothing it it, either of Proſit or Pleaſure: But yet is a Sin that hath got into all parts, into Courts and Cities, into Towns and Vil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lages, to the Country Man at his Plow and Cart, and the Shop-keeper in his Shop, to bind every little Bargain; to bloat up a vain Diſcourſe, and to back every giddy Paſſion.</p>
            <p>We have lived in an Age, wherein Hell hath been as it were let looſe, and Rioting and Drunkenneſs, Cham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bering and Wantonneſs, Luxury and Intemperance have been very faſhionable Accompliſhments; and Sin hath been grown downright impudent, and hath outfac'd the Sun at Noon-day.</p>
            <p>Whereas formerly, as the Apoſtle tells us; that they
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:98198:12"/>
               <hi>that were drunk, were drunk in the Night,</hi> as being the proper time to conceal ſuch Works of Darkneſs. Now we have had not only Night-Revellings, but Day-ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſes with a witneſs: And whereas the Proverb uſed to be <hi>as drunk as a Beggar,</hi> I am ſorry to ſay, that thoſe of higher Quality have ſeemed to envy the Beggar's good Name.</p>
            <p>Sin hath taken Heart, and hath dared to ſhow it ſelf, and come abroad in Pomp, having had the Examples and Encouragements of Perſons of all Places and Quali<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties to countenance and back it; ſo that there hath obtained almoſt an univerſal Corruption of Manners. And then Uncleanneſs follows as the natural Conſequent of all this, and is always the Companion of a looſe and wicked Age.</p>
            <p>As for Divine Worſhip and Adoration due to the great Creator of our Beings, and our continual Preſerver and Benefactor, how little hath it been regarded by moſt Perſons and Families, and by many even on the Chriſtian Sabbath it ſelf? That Day which hath been ſet apart for Divine Service and Worſhip, for devout Meditations and pious Works, hath been made with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny a meer Market-day of Debauchery, the beſt Day that the Devil hath, and <hi>the worſt day of all the Week:</hi> or elſe a time of meer Viſit and Idleneſs, except what is juſt ſpent in ſome parts perhaps of the publick Service, and which Men have been quite weary of too: Yea how hath all that is Divine, been expoſed by Men of corrupt Minds; the Holy Scripture it ſelf burleſqued and drol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed at? and how hath it been the Pride and Glory of wanton Wits to dare to ſpeak againſt Heaven, and to make a Scoff of Immortality: Religion hath been de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cried in the Streets: true Seriouſneſs and Strictneſs have been eſteemed a Crime: Formality and a ſiery Zeal for particular Forms and Parties, for Ceremonies
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:98198:13"/>and outward Garbs, hath been with too too many thought a ſufficient Commutation for ſubſtantial Piety and good Works; to bow at the Name of Jeſus, and to be zealous for Church and Liturgy, muſt atone with many for all manner of Debaucheries and Immoralities.</p>
            <p>And what Bitterneſs and Envy have been among Neighbours? How few have been clothed with Humi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity, or have put on Charity, which is the Bond of Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectneſs? But hard Cenſures, and unjuſt Surmiſes, Slan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders and Backbitings, Hatred and Strife have prevailed among thoſe that ſhould have lived together in mutual Love and Kindneſs. Families and Neighbourhoods have been the Theater of unchriſtian Feuds: and how have thoſe that are joined in the ſame Societies, rejoic'd in one anothers Falls and Miſeries.</p>
            <p>Yea, Religion it ſelf, which ſhould have meekned and united our Hearts, hath been the very thing that our Contentions and Differences have been moſt about: and that Charity which ſhould be the proper Character of Chriſtians, as it is the very Spirit of the Goſpel, hath been laid aſide, as if it did not concern us, and Fury and Animoſity have been taken up inſtead of it: It hath been thought a commendable Quality to be fierce againſt all, that would not entertain their Notions of things, that they could even call down for Fire from Heaven up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them to conſume them.</p>
            <p>Mens <hi>Feet have run to Evil, and they have made haſte to ſhed innocent Blood; their Thoughts are Thoughts of Ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity; Waſting and Deſtruction are in their Paths; and the way of Peace have they not known. Judgment hath been turned away backward, and Juſtice ſtood afar off: Yea Truth faileth, and he that departsth from evil, hath made himſelf a Prey,</hi> As the Words of the Prophet are, <hi>Iſa.</hi> 57.7, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Which of <hi>Judah</hi>'s Sins have we not had among us? Yea I may ſay, which of <hi>Sodom</hi>'s Sins? And all this in a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:98198:13"/>Land of Light, which hath been lifted up to Heaven in many Bleſſings and Priviledges, and which profeſſes to receive and ſubmit to the Holy Inſtitutions and Rules of the Bleſſed Jeſus, by whom ſure we are taught quite other things. If the rude and barbarous Indians or Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of ſome cruel or Dunghil Deity, ſhould wallow in all Licentiouſneſs, or ſhould like Beaſts of Prey devour and tear one another, it would be no ſuch ſtrange thing: For this would ſatisfy beſt the Fiends they ſerve. But our Saviour hath wrote us another Copy, and hath pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed us Rules of the greateſt Purity, Self-Denial, Love and Condeſcenſion to one another. And this is our Profeſſion.</p>
            <p>And therefore this muſt needs be a mighty Aggrava<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of our Crimes, and might give us a juſt Expecta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of another ſort of Treatment from the Almighty. Well might God have ſaid to us, <hi>Ah, I will eaſe me of my Adverſaries, and I will avenge me of my Enemies.</hi> And we might have <hi>grop'd for the Wall like the Blind,</hi> for Support and Direction, and yet might not have found it. <hi>We might have roared all like Bears, and mourned ſore like Doves; and look'd for Judgment, but have found none; for Salvation, which might have been far from us.</hi> This we might ſurely have expected, if Providence had mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſured out to us in his Diſpenſations that which we had deſerved. So that what ſhall we ſay?</p>
            <p>And is not our Deliverance then of meer Mercy? God himſelf hath <hi>put on the Helmet of Salvation upon his Head for us, and hath put on the Garments of Venge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for Clothing, and was clad with Zeal as a Cloak: and when the Enemy was coming in like a Flood upon us, the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of the Lord hath lift up a Standard againſt him.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let us therefore ſay with the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul, and all that is within me bleſs his Holy Name. Bleſs the Lord, O my Soul, and forget not all his Bene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fits:
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:98198:14"/>Who forgiveth all thine Iniquities, and healeth all thy Diſeaſes. Who redeemeth thy Life from Deſtruction; who crowneth thee with Loving-kindneſs and tender Mercies.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. But then it is likewiſe to be conſidered in this Duty of Praiſe, that we ſhow our thankful Acceptance of the Mercy, by our united Studies and earneſt Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers to have that perfected which is begun, and now it is come to ſo good a paſs, that it may not meet with any thing to obſtruct the deſired end.</p>
            <p>If there be any Value for ſo great a Mercy, and if we do really carry a grateful ſenſe of it upon our Hearts; if we would not relapſe into our former Troubles and Fears, but would ſee a laſting Peace in our <hi>Iſrael,</hi> we ſhould labour to prevent whatſoever may hinder the full Attainment of a bleſſed Iſſue, and we ſhould with joint Endeavours and ſtrong Cries to the God of all Counſel and Grace, do our very utmoſt to accompliſh ſo glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous a Work.</p>
            <p>And if we do our parts, we need not doubt, but that he who hath ſo mercifully given out his helping-Hand thus far, will be as ready to aſſiſt in what remains. For if he had a mind to deſtroy us, ſurely he would not have done us all this good.</p>
            <p>But we muſt not think to dally with Providence, and to have it even at our Beck or Command. If we play away this day of Grace, and neglect the Seaſon, or if we divide into Fractions, and run into parties, we muſt not think to be ſaved againſt our Will.</p>
            <p>God hath once more put an Opportunity in our hands, wherein we may make our ſelves happy, if we will conſider the things that make for our Peace. And if we let this paſs, we do not know whether ever we may have ſuch another.</p>
            <p>If it ſhould at laſt miſcarry for want of our continual united Concurrence, it will be in vain for us to pretend
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:98198:14"/>an Eſteem of the preſent Providence, or a Zeal to our Religion, when we ſtill ſacrifice the publick Good to our private Intereſt or unchriſtian Reſentments. But if it ſhould be ſo indeed, we can expect no other but to be the Scorn and Deriſion of all Nations, and the Triumph of our enraged Enemies, as we ſhall be really a blot to the Engliſh Name and Reformed Religion; and our Poſterity after us may have too much cauſe to curſe us for the ſtupidſt Generation that ever was.</p>
            <p>But then, moreover, if we are truly ſenſible of the Greatneſs of the preſent Mercy to our ſelves, and if there be any Grain of Chriſtian Charity left in us, we cannot but pity thoſe that want it, and ſhall be as earneſt on their Behalf, that they may partake of the like; and as the Church here prays further, that God would <hi>turn their Captivity as the Streams of the South,</hi> and that they who <hi>have ſowed in Tears, may at length reap in Joy:</hi> So let us pray in the Behalf of our poor Brethren, with the deepeſt and moſt yearning Compaſſion.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>O remember not againſt thy Servants former Iniquities; Let thy tender Mercies ſpeedily prevent them; for they are brought very low; Help them, O God of our Salvation, for the Glory of thy Name, and deliver them: Wherefore ſhould the Heathen ſay, Where is now their God? Let him be known among the Heathen in our ſight: And let the Sighing of the Priſoners come before thee, according to the Greatneſs of thy Power: So we thy People and Sheep of thy Paſture, will give thee Thanks for ever; we will ſhew forth thy Praiſe to all Generations.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. The laſt thing that I ſhall mention that is to be conſidered in this Duty of Praiſe is, that we manifeſt the Sincerity of our Gratitude by a ſerious Study of A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendment and Reformation, that it may not repent the Lord, what he hath done for us. For <hi>after all that is come upon us for our evil Deeds, and for our great Treſpaſſes,
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:98198:15"/>ſeeing that our God hath puniſhed us leſs than our Iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties deſerve, and hath given us ſuch Deliverance as this, ſhould we again break his Commandments?</hi> Then ſaith <hi>Ezra, Wouldſt not thou be angry with us, till thou hadſt conſumed us, ſo that there ſhould be no Remnant nor eſcaping?</hi> Ezr. 9.13, 14.</p>
            <p>We muſt not think that we are therefore delivered, to work Wickedneſs, or that we may ſin with the great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er Boldneſs. God hath a Divine and Holy end in this and all his Diſpenſations towards us; as <hi>Luke</hi> 1.69. <hi>He hath raiſed up an Horn of Salvation for us, that we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing delivered out of the Hands of our Enemies, might ſerve him without Fear in Righteouſneſs and Holineſs before him all the Days of our Lives.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We muſt not think that we are delivered from Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to ſerve our own Luſts; which is every whit as dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gerous an Idolatry, as to bow to dumb Images, and to ſerve Stocks and Stones.</p>
            <p>We muſt not think that we are ſaved from Errours in our Faith and Doctrine, that we may have worſe in our Lives. For there is no ſuch Errour and Hereſy in the World, as a bad Life and a wicked Heart.</p>
            <p>And we muſt not think, that our Liberties and Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perties are preſerved, that we may revel more with them in Wantonneſs and Exceſs. If our Laws and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment are preſerved, yet that will little avail us, if we do not govern our ſelves well, and our own Affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons and Paſſions. It is not the ſaving of our Laws will ſave us, if we are lawleſs in our own Spirits.</p>
            <p>If we are ſecured from outward Tyranny, what will that ſignify, if our Sins and Corruptions within do ſtill tyrannize over us? the World or Sin in our Hearts will be a worſe Tyrant to us, than ever any Prince that could ſit upon the Throne. The Pope or French King could never hurt us, as our own evil Affections can.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="25" facs="tcp:98198:15"/>It had been better a thouſand times, that our Bodies had been hack'd and maſſacred at the command of furious Jeſuits, or that we had been Slaves for ever to the moſt cruel Lords, if thereby our Virtue and Innocency might have been preſerved, than that we ſhould be the Devils Martyrs, or be living Slaves to the World and Fleſh. It is a Reformation, that God intends in what he hath done for us; and that is it therefore, which we ſhould alſo intend.</p>
            <p>Let not our Deliverance lull us aſleep in Security. For if we do not make that Divine and Holy uſe of it as we ought, God can quickly turn his Hand upon us in Fury. And though one In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrument be gone, he can quickly ſind out another to puniſh us; or he can eaſily make us a Puniſhment to our ſelves, if he ſhould but ſuffer an evil Spirit of Diviſion and Diſcord to ſeize upon us. God hath Axes and Hammers enough at command, that he can make uſe of to chaſtiſe us, if yet all he hath done, doth us no good.</p>
            <p>As we ſind in the Hiſtory of the Judges, that when the People corrupted themſelves after their Deliverance, God ſoon raiſed up other Enemies, that a long time kept them in hard Bondage, till they repented themſelves of their Sins, and then the Lord heard their Groanings, and ſaved them.</p>
            <p>Jer. 7. 8. <hi>Ye truſt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in lying Words, that cannot profit,</hi> if ye think you may ſin ſecurely, and becauſe of preſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>nt Mercies that yet ſhall be henceforth out of Danger: <hi>Will ye ſteal, murder and commit Adultery, and ſwear falſly,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>And come and ſtand before me in this Houſe, which is called by my Name, and ſay, We are delivered to do all theſe Aborninations?</hi> No. <hi>But go ye unto my place, which is at</hi> Shiloh, <hi>where I ſet my Name at the firſt, and ſee what I did to it for the Wickedneſs of my People</hi> Iſrael. So what Calamities and Miſeries have befallen other Churches and Countries, and how can you but expect the like, if you do not take warning by their Falls. <hi>Thus ſaith the Lord of Hiſts. The God of</hi> Iſrael <hi>amend your Ways and your Doings, and I will cauſe you to dwell in this place.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>We are told by the Pſalmiſt, <hi>Pſal.</hi> 33.12. <hi>That bleſſed is the Nation wh<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> hath the Lord for their God, and bleſſed is the People whom he hath choſen for his Inheritance.</hi> For if God be for us, who can be againſt us? If the Eternal God will be our Refuge, and will but put under the everlaſting Arms, who is he that can hurt us? So that the greateſt thing we can do towards our own Happineſs, is to engage the mighty God to be on our ſide, and to ſecure his gracious and bleſſed Preſence, that it may be ever with us.</p>
            <p>But then for this we muſt ſee, that we depart from all Iniquity;
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:98198:16"/>for he is not a God that hath Pleaſure in Wickedneſs, neither can Evil dwell with him: We muſt ſee that we walk before him, and be perfect: For his Eyes run to and fro, to ſhow himſelf ſtrong in the Behalf of them that walk uprightly; then he will be with us, and ſave us, and he will never leave us, nor forſake us, if we keep his Covenant and his Teſtimonies.</p>
            <p>We have plainly ſeen, that the Lord's hand is not ſhortned, that it cannot ſave; neither is his Ear heavy, that it cannot hear; and he is the ſame God yeſterday, to day, and for ever. But let us ſee, that we do not at laſt provoke him to leave us by our Sins; let us ſee that our Iniquities do not ſeparate between us and our God.</p>
            <p>He ſeemed for our Sins to threaten us ſore, and to write bitter things againſt us; but he hath not yet done <hi>his Work, his ſtrange Work; he hath not brought to paſs his Act, his ſtrange Act.</hi> As the Work of Judgment is called, becauſe he is ſlow to anger; <hi>Iſa.</hi> 28.21. Let us ſee, that we do not provoke him by our Sins to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn upon us in Fury.</p>
            <p>It ſeems as if our gracious God had had a Diſpute with himſelf, not to do with us as once he had about the People of <hi>Iſrael,</hi> Hoſ. 11.8. <hi>How ſhall I give thee up</hi> Ephraim? <hi>How ſhall I deliver thee</hi> Iſrael? <hi>How ſhall I make thee as</hi> Admah? <hi>How ſhall I ſet thee as</hi> Zeboim? <hi>My Heart is turned within me; my Repentings are kindled together. I will not execute the Fierceneſs of mine Anger; I will not return to deſtroy</hi> Ephraim: <hi>For I am God, and not Man, the Holy one in the midſt of thee.</hi> So that at length Mercy hath prevailed over Judgment, and we are ſaved as it is this Day.</p>
            <p>And now ſhall not the Goodneſs of God lead us to Repentance? ſhall we no better improve, but baſely deſpiſe the Riches of his Goodneſs, and Forbearance, and Long-ſuffering? ſhould we ſtill continue to walk after our Hardneſs and impenitent Heart? What would this be, but to treaſure up to our ſelves Wrath againſt the Day of Wrath and Revelation of the righteous Judgment of God, which yet we may expect, if we ſhould continue to do wickedly?</p>
            <p>It is propheſied of Mount <hi>Sion,</hi> Obad. 17. That <hi>upon</hi> Sion <hi>ſhall be Deliverance, and there ſhall be Holineſs, and then the Houſe of</hi> Jacob <hi>ſhall poſſeſs their Poſſeſſions.</hi> Why ſhould it not be ſo with us? Why ſhould not Deliverance and Holineſs go together? And then might we hope, that we ſhould dwell in a peaceable Habitati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and in ſure Dwellings, and in quiet reſting places. And,</p>
            <p>Surely if ever any Nation had cauſe to love and ſerve the great and Holy God, we ought to think our ſelves under the ſtricteſt
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:98198:16"/>Obligations in the World to do ſo. For (as <hi>Moſes</hi> once ſaid to the <hi>Jews</hi>) <hi>What Nation is there ſo great, who hath God ſo nigh unto them, as the Lord our God is in all things that we call upon him for? What Nation is there ſo great, that hath Statutes and Judgments ſo righteous?</hi> And what Nation is there that hath had ſo great Communications of Light and Love, as we have had?</p>
            <p>How early were the Thoughts of God for good to us in the days of our Fore-fathers for many Generations paſt? How ſoon did the Sun of Righteouſneſs ariſe upon this Ioneſom Iſle, this <hi>ulti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma Thule,</hi> at the Ends of the Earth, and the day-ſpring from on high did viſit us, when many other Nations for a long time ſat in Darkneſs and ſaw no Light?</p>
            <p>How ſoon had Chriſtianity here a legal Eſtabliſhment, and the ſupream Authority and Power embrac'd and encouraged it, when in other places our Holy Religion was frowned at, and perſecuted by thoſe that ſhould have been nurſing-Fathers and nurſing-Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers to it?</p>
            <p>And when for the Negligence and Sins of its Profeſſours, a long Night of Darkneſs had overtaken us, as it had alſo in moſt other Churches, yet now bleſſed be God, for a good while this Night hath been ſpent, and the Luſtre of Divine Truth hath gloriouſly ariſen again and ſhone upon us.</p>
            <p>And when in many other places this bleſſed Reformation hath continually had the Powers of the Earth conteſting againſt it, ſo that it could never get into the Throne; here it was begun at firſt, and hath been carried on and protected by publick Conſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutions, by our Princes and Laws: ſo that the Profeſſion of that Religion that hath been a matter of great Trouble and Difficulty to others, becauſe of the Diſcountenance and Oppoſitions it hath met with from thoſe in Authority, hath been hardly a Virtue to us, who have had the Laws and Authority to encourage us to em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it, whereby it hath become as well our Intereſt, as our Duty.</p>
            <p>And notwithſtanding all the repeated Deſigns, the deep and cloſe Combinations of our Enemies to overturn, overturn, over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turn all again, yet how little have they been able to prevail? He that ſitteth in the Heavens hath laugh'd, the Lord hath had them in Deriſion.</p>
            <p>The Archers have ſorely grieved, and <hi>have ſhot at us, and hated us, but our Bow hath abode in Strength, and the Arms of our Hands have been made ſtrong, by the Hands of the mighty God of</hi> Jacob, who hath helped us and bleſſed us.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="28" facs="tcp:98198:17"/>We have had the <hi>Bleſſings of Heaven above, and the Bleſſings of the deep that lieth under; we have had the Bleſſings of the Breaſt and of the Womb;</hi> we have had the <hi>upper and nether Springs; and our Bleſſings have prevailed above the Bleſſings of our Progenitours.</hi> And the Lord hath ſtill eſtabliſhed us an Holy People unto himſelf, that all the Earth may ſee, that we are called by his Name.</p>
            <p>We have been a Nation, that hath flowed with Riches, Wealth and Honour; ſo that we have been both the Admiration and Envy of many about us. We have wanted nothing; we have had Plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty of all things; we have had Glory and Power; we have been able to help our Friends, and have not feared our Enemies.</p>
            <p>Now indeed we were almoſt fallen, had not our Almighty De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liverer graciouſly prevented us, and found out help for us, who uſed to have the Honour in that kind to give, and not to receive.</p>
            <p>But now if after all this Kindneſs that hath been ſhowed us, if after all this that hath been done for us, we ſhould ſin againſt him, and ſhould caſt his Commandments behind our Backs, what Tongue were able to expreſs our Ingratitude?</p>
            <p>Surely God hath planted us <hi>a Noble Vine,</hi> and in <hi>a very fruitful Hill.</hi> And never was any Vineyard ſo fenc'd, and ſecured, and watched over, as we have been by our careful Protectour. In a Word, <hi>What could have been done more for us, than what God hath done for us?</hi> But now when he <hi>look'd, that we ſhould bring forth Grapes, have we not brought forth wild Grapes?</hi> Hath not our Vine been degenerated, and become as <hi>the Vine of</hi> Sodom, <hi>and of the Fields of</hi> Gomorrah? And have not our <hi>Grapes been Grapes of Gall, and our Wine the Poiſon of Dragons, and the cruel Venom of Aſps?</hi> Therefore may we not wonder, that God hath not taken away his Hedg that was about us, and laid us waſte? As he threatned once to do to the <hi>Jews</hi> for the like reaſon, <hi>Iſai.</hi> 5. But now he is pleaſed to wait a while longer upon us; but if after all, we do not anſwer his La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour and Coſt, let us look to our ſelves. He is prevailed upon by the Prayers of his Servants, as we find it in the Parable of the barren Fig-tree, to try us a while longer, <hi>Luke</hi> 13.8, 9. <hi>Lord, let it alone this Year alſo, till I ſhall dig about it and dung it; And if it bear Fruit, well; and if not, then after that thou ſhalt cut it down.</hi> Our Fruitfulneſs under our Mercies muſt prevent our Ruin.</p>
            <p>We find in the Epiſtle, that was written to the Church of <hi>Ephe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus,</hi> Rev. 2.1, &amp;c. that though that Church had ſuffered much for their Profeſſion, and was free from thoſe groſs Corruptions that had inſected other Churches by the Errours of the <hi>Nicolai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tans,
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:98198:17"/>Yet I have ſomewhat againſt thee,</hi> ſaith our Saviour, <hi>Becauſe thou haſt left thy firſt Love;</hi> and for that he is much diſpleaſed: <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>member therefore from whence thou art fallen, and repent,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>or elſe I will come unto thee quickly, and remove thy Candleſtick out of his place, except thou repent.</hi> But we are not only fallen from our firſt Love, but have been grown greatly corrupt. We have quite loſt our Fore-Fathers Zeal, and inſtead of being better by our former means, we are become worſe and worſe. The old Engliſh Gravi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty and Seriouſneſs is gone, and we have ſtrived to out do the deeds of the Wicked. And yet we are ſpared and delivered.</p>
            <p>God threatned to ſpue out of his Mouth the Church of the <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odiceans,</hi> for being <hi>neither hot nor cold,</hi> Rev. 3.15. And ſurely if Lukewarmneſs in Religion be ſuch a Provocation, 'tis a wonder that this had not been our Lot. We have been hot indeed, where we ſhould have been cold; hot in our Wickedneſs, Uncharitable<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and unbrotherly Carriage; but in true Godlineſs, Love and doing good to Men we have ſeemed to be as if there were neither Life nor Soul in us.</p>
            <p>And as was ſaid to the Church of <hi>Sardis,</hi> Have we not alſo had <hi>a Name to live, and yet are dead?</hi> Surely at beſt our Works have not been <hi>perfect before God.</hi> And there he threatned to come on them, as <hi>a Thief,</hi> if they did <hi>not watch, ſo that they ſhould not know <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>n what Hour he would come upon them.</hi> This is partly true of us now; he hath come on us indeed like a Thief, as to the Sudden<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs of it; but it hath not been to kill and deſtroy; but in one Hour, as it were is all this Salvation unexpectedly wrought: <hi>Surely we have ſeen ſtrange things to day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>And now conſidering his wonderful Grace and Kindneſs to us, together with our former Sins and Ingratitude; 'tis high time for <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s to awake to Repentance, and to give up our ſelves to him in an Holy intire Obedience.</p>
            <p>We muſt repent then of our paſt Wickedneſs, and ſet up a preſent Reformation, that our Mercies may be laſting to us, and may be intailed upon the Generations to come. We had need all of us mourn, <hi>every Family apart; the Family of the Houſe of</hi> Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid, <hi>and the Family of the Houſe of</hi> Nathan, <hi>and the Family of the Houſe of</hi> Levi, <hi>and the Family of</hi> Shimei. And it doth not at all an become the Solemnity of this Day, when we are returning Thanks for Mercies, yet bitterly to bewail our Sins, which inhance the Greatneſs of God's Mercy to us, and might have juſtly made us to have expected other things. And O that God would be pleaſed
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:98198:18"/>to pour out a Spirit of <hi>Prayer and Supplication</hi> upon all Fleſh among us for that End!</p>
            <p>But we muſt not only reflect with Sorrow upon times paſt, our chief Work is yet to come. And that is, that we labour for a tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row and National Reformation; which though we that are in pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vate Capacities cannot do much to, yet we ſhould labour to do what we can; that as we have contributed to the national Guilt, by our Omiſſions and evil Practices and Examples, ſo now we may by the ſame ways promote a National Repentance: And what we cannot do our ſelves, let us help by our devout and earneſt Prayers at the Throne of Grace, that Holineſs beginning at the Throne, may flow down through all the Channels of Office and Magiſtracy to the meaneſt Perſon of the Land.</p>
            <p>Let not Holineſs ſuffer for the Miſcarriages of ſome of its Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours. But let Piety come into Reputation again; and let it be an Honour to Men to be as good as may be; which would ſoon be, if all in high place would publickly own and defend it. We have good Laws already, that all agree in, for the ſuppreſſing of all Irreligion and Immorality: There is no party can have the Face to deſire and beg a Toleration here. Let theſe be put into Execution; and let Vice be outfac'd, that hath been ſo bold and impudent among us ſo long. If Men will rant and damn, and ſwear and be drunk, let them do it in Corners; but let them not dare to appear abroad to infect others by their peſtilent Breath. If Men will dare to affront God, and commit Villanies and Exceſs, let them be ſtigmatized, and let a Mark be ſet upon them, that they may become the Obſervation and Scorn of all, if they forfeit Pity by their Irreclaimableneſs. If Men will not become truly religious, yet however they ought to be kept from abuſing Religion.</p>
            <p>There is no civiliz'd Nation, but hath always thought Religion and Vertue its greateſt Honour and Intereſt. Atheiſts themſelves will allow that 'tis convenient for the publick Good. And there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thoſe that decry and diſcourage it, or give Countenance to Irreligion and Sin, ought to be accounted the very Peſts of Man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kind, and are really the worſt of Traitors and Enemies, that any State can have: And the greateſt Kindneſs therefore that we can ſhow to our Native Country, is, by becoming truly religious and good. This is the way to engage God on our ſide, to prevent the Miſcarrying of that Deliverance at laſt, that hath had ſo bleſſed a Beginning, and to obtain a Bleſſing upon the publick Counſels and Endeavours, and doth in its own Nature tend to promote the Honour, the Quiet, and the Happineſs of the Land.</p>
            <p>
               <pb n="31" facs="tcp:98198:18"/>If Parents would be religious in educating their Children, and would but take as much Pains to inſtruct and nurture them up in the Knowledg of God, as they do teach them any Arts and Sciences. If rich Men and Gentlemen would be religious, and there<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> by influence their poor Neighbours to like and practiſe the ſame. If publick Officers would be religious, and reſtrain Sin, as they might, by their Example and Authority. If they that teach others to be religious, would be truly religious themſelves, and become Examples of it to the Flock, then we ſhould ſoon have as it were new Heavens and a new Earth; and if we would but thus do our Duty to God and our Neighbour, we may be ſure he will not fail to pour down his Bleſſings upon us.</p>
            <p>Let us therefore all conſider our ways; and as now we rejoice and are glad at the great and ſtrange things that God hath done for us, let us ſee that we make a grateful Return to God of a ſui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table Obedience; let Religion be our Study in all its parts; let us keep his Sabbaths, and obſerve his Ordinances; let us read and ſtudy his Word to this end that we may be better, and let our De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light be in the Law of the Lord; let us tremble at his Name, and do his Will; let us fly from Sin, and mortify our Luſts; let us par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticularly ſee that we remember the new Commandment of our bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed Saviour, that we love one another, and that we live together as Brethren: Let us conſider, that Religion doth not conſiſt in Meat and Drink, but in Righteouſneſs and Peace and Joy in the Holy Ghoſt.</p>
            <p>And let this our <hi>Sion be filled with Judgment and Righteouſneſs: And Oh that Wiſdom and Knowledg may be the Stability of our times and Strength of our Salvation, and that the Fear of the Lord may be our Treaſure: Then the Work of Righteouſneſs ſhall be Peace, and the Effect of Righteouſneſs, Quietneſs and Aſſurance for ever; then Violence ſhall no more be heard in our Land, nor Waſting and Deſtruction in all our Bor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders; but we ſhall call our Walls Salvation, and our Gates Praiſe. And the Lord ſhall be unto us an everlaſting Light, and our God, our Glory. The Sun ſhall no more go down, neither ſhall the Moon with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw her ſelf: For the Lord ſhall be our everlaſting Light, and the Days of our Mourning ſhall be ended.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:98198:19"/>
            <head>
               <hi>Books lately Printed and Sold by</hi> Jonathan <hi>Robinſon, at the Golden Lion in St.</hi> Pauls <hi>Church-yard, relating to the great Revolutions and Affairs in</hi> England, 1688, 1689.</head>
            <list>
               <item>AN Account of the Reaſons of the Nobility and Gentry's Invitation of the Prince of <hi>Orange</hi> into <hi>England;</hi> Being a <hi>Memorial</hi> from the Engliſh Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants concerning their Grievances; with a large Account of the Birth of the Prince of <hi>Wales:</hi> preſented to their Highneſſes the Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>A Collection of Political and Hiſtorical Papers relating to the Preſent, Juncture of Affairs in <hi>England,</hi> in eleven Parts; which will be Continued from Time to Time, according as Matter occurs.</item>
               <item>A Brief Hiſtory of the Succeſſion of the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> &amp;c. Collected out of the Records, and the moſt Authentick Hiſtorians; written for the Satis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faction of the Nation.</item>
               <item>Wonderful Predictions of <hi>Noſtredamus, Grebner, David Pareus,</hi> and <hi>Autonius Torquatus;</hi> wherein the Grandeur of their Preſent Majeſties, the Happineſs of <hi>England,</hi> and Downfall of <hi>France</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> are plainly Delineated. With a large Preface, ſhewing, That the Crown of <hi>England,</hi> has not been obſcurely foretold to their Majeſties <hi>William</hi> the 3d, and Queen <hi>Mary,</hi> late Prince and Princeſs of <hi>Orange;</hi> and that the People of this Ancient Monarchy have duly contributed thereunto, in the preſent Aſſembly of Lords and <hi>Commons,</hi> notwithſtanding the Objections of Men of different Extremes.</item>
               <item>
                  <hi>Julian's</hi> Arts to Undermine and Extirpate Chriſtianity, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> By <hi>Samuel Johnſon.</hi> The Impreſſion of which Book was made in the Year 1683, and has ever ſince <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>in buried under the Ruins of all thoſe Engliſh Rights which it endeavoured to defend; but by the Auſpicious and Happy Arrival of the Prince of <hi>Orange,</hi> both They and It have obtained a Reſurrection.</item>
               <item>The Myſtery of Iniquity working in the Dividing of Proteſtants, in order to the ſubverting of Religion, and our Laws, for almoſt the ſpace of thirty Years laſt paſt, plainly laid open. With ſome Advices to Proteſtants of all Perſwaſions, in the preſent Juncture of our Affairs. To which is added, A Specimen of a Bill for uniting of Proteſtants.</item>
               <item>Liberty of Conſcience now highly neceſſary for <hi>England,</hi> humbly repreſented to this preſent Parliament.</item>
               <item>A Friendly Debate between Dr. <hi>Kingſman,</hi> a diſſatisfied Clergy-man, and <hi>Gratia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus Trimmer,</hi> a Neighbour Miniſter, concerning the late Thankſgiving-Day; the Prince's Deſcent into <hi>England;</hi> the Nobility and Gentries joining with him; the Acts of the Honourable Convention; the Nature of our Engliſh Government; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>e Secret League with <hi>France;</hi> the Oaths of Allegiance and Supremacy, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> With ſome Conſiderations on Biſhop <hi>Sanderſon</hi> and Dr. <hi>Falkner,</hi> about Monarchy, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> Written for the Satisfaction of ſome of the Clergy, and others that <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> under Scruples. By a Miniſter of the Church of <hi>England.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap> reproved, in a Sermon on 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 10.10. By <hi>Mr. Hopkins.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <pb facs="tcp:98198:19"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
